Finding Aid for Edward Pierce Papers, 1960s-1987 and 1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward Pierce Papers 1960s-1987, 1996
Pierce, Edward, 1930-
5 linear feet
89190 Aa 2
Dr. Edward Pierce was active in both medicine and politics in Michigan. He was well-known for his conception of and work at the Summit Medical Center in Ann Arbor, Michigan, a center offering medical services for low-income individuals. His political career included a seat on the Ann Arbor City Council, a term as Michigan State Senator and Mayor of Ann Arbor. The papers relate primarily to his political career, with the bulk of the papers focusing on his term as mayor of Ann Arbor from 1985 to 1987. Other papers refer to his campaigns for Congress, Senate, and governor.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mayoral records donated by Dr. Pierce, April 1987 (Donor no. 7436 ); Additional records (primarily pre-mayoral) donated September 2005 by Judge Lynne Pierce (Donor no. 9647 )
The collection is open to research.
Dr. Edward Pierce was born in Three Rivers, Michigan on January 3, 1930 and settled in Ann Arbor in 1940. Receiving both his Bachelor's degree (in 1955) and his Medical degree (in 1959) from the University of Michigan, Dr. Edward Pierce set up a family practice in Ann Arbor in 1960. Dr. Pierce was well-known for his conception of and work at the Summit Medical Center Medical Center in Ann Arbor, a center offering medical services for low-income individuals. From 1974 to 1975 and 1989 to 1990 he was the Chairman of the Department of Family Practice at St. Joseph Mercy Hospital. In 1996, Dr. Pierce began Merian's Friends, a physician-aid-in-dying group.
He also was active in politics as well, first serving on the Ann Arbor City Council from 1964 to 1966, a term as Michigan State Senator in 1979, and mayor of Ann Arbor from 1985 to 1987. In 1974 and 1976, he ran for Congress, but lost. In 1982, he ran for Michigan governor in the Democratic primary, losing to James Blanchard.
Dr. Pierce passed away on July 4, 2002.
Dr. Pierce's papers relate primarily to his political career, with the bulk of the papers focusing on his term as Mayor of Ann Arbor from 1985 to 1987. Other papers document his campaigns for Congress, Senate, and governor.
The papers are divided into five series: Pre-Mayoral files, Mayoral files, Post-Mayoral files, Photographs, and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Pierce, Edward, 1930-; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Elections--Michigan--1974.; Elections--Michigan--1976.; Elections--Michigan--1978.; Elections--Michigan--1982.; Elections--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Legislators--Michigan.; Mayors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor Farmers' Market.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Markets.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Mayors.; Legislators--Michigan.; Markets--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Mayors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Pierce, Edward, 1930-; Political elections--Michigan.; Politics and government--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Pre-Mayoral files 1960-1987
  The Pre-Mayoral series (0.5 linear ft., 1960-1987) documents Pierce's campaigns for Congress, Senate, governor and mayor as well as other political campaigns. The papers primarily include position papers, speeches, interviews, and correspondence.
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Early campaign 1960s (Box 1)
  - Mayor's Race
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
  - Congress
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Senate 1978-1982 (Box 1)
  - Governor's Race
    - Position papers 1982 (Box 1)
    - Campaign notes 1982 (Box 1)
    - Campaign material and photographs, 1982 (Box 1)
- Mayoral files 1985-1987
  The Mayoral papers (5 linear ft., 1985-1987) include subject files on municipal administration, correspondence with residents, proclamations, resident complaint file, appointment books and calendar, and photographs.
  - Topical files 1985-1987
    (includes some earlier papers)
    - Affirmative action/comparable worth (Box 1)
    - AIDS (Box 1)
    - Peter Allen (Box 1)
    - Alliance Bible Fellowship (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Cantata Singers (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor News (Box 1)
      (police lawsuit)
    - Ann Arbor Summer Festival, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Township (Box 1)
    - Annual report (Box 1)
    - Ann Street-Ashley parking structure, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Anti-smoking (Box 1)
    - Appleridge Apartments (Box 1)
    - Arboretum (Box 1)
    - Arbor Main Place, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Area Plan East/N. East (Box 1)
    - Arrowwood Hills Cooperative (Box 1)
    - Arts (Box 1)
    - Ashley Plaza (Box 1)
    - Audit
      - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Blanchard, James (Box 1)
    - Bond and millage issues 1974-1985 (Box 1)
    - Board of Commissioners, Washtenaw County (Box 1)
    - Budget
      - FY 1985-1986 (Box 1)
      - Requests FY 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Bugajski, Joe (Box 1)
    - Bullard, Perry (Box 1)
    - Building and safety (Box 1)
    - Cablevision (Box 1)
    - Capital Improvements budget (Box 1)
    - Central America (Box 1)
    - Child care (Box 1)
    - City
      - Federal relations (Box 2)
      - University Coordinating Committee (Box 2)
      - University of Michigan relations (Box 2)
    - Civil liberties (Box 2)
    - Clean Water Act (Box 2)
    - Communications, miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Community Mental Health, Washtenaw County (Box 2)
    - Contracts -- Union/city (Box 2)
    - Cooper, Daniel (Box 2)
    - Cope-O'Brien Center, Washtenaw County (Box 2)
    - Corrections, Department of (Box 2)
    - Council Contingency (Box 2)
    - Crime (Box 2)
    - Denver Boot (Box 2)
    - Discrimination (Box 2)
    - Domestic violence (Box 2)
    - Downtown Conference Center (Box 2)
    - Energy (Box 2)
    - Exmoor extension (Box 2)
    - Financial report, city, FY 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Fire protection (Box 2)
    - Food (Box 2)
    - Gallup Park (Box 2)
    - Gay/lesbian (Box 2)
    - Glacier Way improvement (Box 2)
    - Grape boycott (Box 2)
    - Handgun controls, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Handicapped material (Box 2)
    - Holidays (Box 2)
    - Holocaust Memorial Council -- U.S. (Box 2)
    - Homeless (Box 2)
    - Hotels (Box 2)
    - Household survey 1986 (Box 2)
    - Housing
      - Code (Box 2)
      - Low cost (Box 2)
      - Low income (Box 2)
      - Public (Box 2)
      - Strategy (Box 2)
    - Human services (Box 2)
    - Huron Plaza, 3 folders (Box 2)
      (Berger Project)
    - Huron River (Box 2)
    - Huron Woods Tech Center (Box 2)
    - Joint Space -- City/County (Box 2)
    - Kerrytown (Box 2)
    - Labor negotiations -- City (Box 2)
    - Levin, Carl (Box 2)
    - Michigan Equity program (Box 2)
    - Michigan State Housing Development Authority (Box 2)
    - Mills Annex (Box 2)
    - Mobile food vendors (Box 2)
    - Northeast-area plaza (Box 2)
    - Nicaraguan connection, 3 folders
      - Nicaragua trip 1986 (Box 2)
    - Nielsen, Bent F. (Box 2)
    - Nursing homes (Box 2)
    - Open Meetings Act (Box 2)
    - Ordinances, proposed/pending (Box 2)
    - Parking, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Parks (Box 3)
    - Pedestrian improvement (Box 3)
    - Pension plans (Box 3)
    - Personal correspondence (Box 3)
    - Pinkertons (Box 3)
    - Planning Law (Box 3)
    - Police
      - Complaints about (Box 3)
      - Investigation of (Box 3)
      - School liaison (Box 3)
    - Politics, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Pollock, Lana (Box 3)
    - Pornography (Box 3)
    - Property taxes (Box 3)
    - Press releases (Box 3)
    - Public Act 312, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Public health (Box 3)
    - Public safety (Box 3)
    - Public service (Box 3)
    - Realtors (Box 3)
    - Retirement
      - City -- general (Box 3)
      - System (Box 3)
    - Scio Township (Box 3)
    - Shopping centers (Box 3)
    - Sidewalks (Box 3)
    - South Africa divestment (Box 3)
    - Space needs (Box 3)
    - Street maintenance (Box 3)
    - Street people (Box 3)
    - Substance abuse (Box 3)
    - Summit Park (Box 3)
    - Tally Hall (Box 3)
    - TANS (Box 3)
      (Tax anticipation notes)
    - Tax abatements (Box 3)
    - Taxes (Box 3)
    - Tower Plaza (Box 3)
    - Towing (Box 3)
    - Townships (Box 3)
      (utilities contracts)
    - Toxic chemicals (Box 3)
    - Traffic (Box 3)
    - Trees (Box 3)
    - Tuebingen Parkway (Box 3)
    - United Nations Day (Box 3)
    - Unemployment (Box 3)
    - Unions -- police and fire (Box 3)
    - Washtenaw County government (Box 3)
    - Washtenaw County Intermediate School District (Box 3)
    - Westover subdivision (Box 3)
    - West Park (Box 3)
    - Wieder, Tom (Box 3)
    - William and First (Box 3)
    - Ypsilanti, City of (Box 3)
  - Organizations
    - AFSCME (Box 3)
    - Ann Arbor Apartment Association (Box 3)
    - Ann Arbor Shelter Association (Box 3)
    - Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce (Box 3)
    - Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra (Box 3)
    - Child Care and Referral Service (Box 3)
    - Citizens for Decency (Box 3)
    - Coalition for Unmet Needs (Box 3)
    - Community Housing Coalition (Box 3)
    - Conference and Visitors Bureau (Box 3)
    - Corner Health Center, the (Box 3)
    - E.R.I.M. (Box 3)
    - Family Support Systems, Inc. (Box 3)
    - Gray Panthers (Box 3)
    - Industrial Technology Institute, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Juvenile Associates of Southeastern Michigan (Box 4)
    - Michigan Theater (Box 4)
    - Michigan Neighborhood Associations (Box 4)
    - Options Center, Inc. (Box 4)
    - Phoenix Human Service Industries, Inc. (Box 4)
    - Private Industry Council (Box 4)
    - Public Schools, Ann Arbor (Box 4)
    - S.O.S. Community Crisis Center (Box 4)
    - Washtenaw Council for the Arts (Box 4)
    - Washtenaw Development Council, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - City Departments
    - Administrator
      - Chizek (Box 4)
      - Collins (Box 4)
      - Mason (Box 4)
    - Airport (Box 4)
    - Assessor (Box 4)
    - Attorney (Box 4)
    - Building (Box 4)
    - Clerk (Box 4)
    - City Council (Box 4)
    - Community Development, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Controller, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Council Rules Commission (Box 4)
    - Courts (Box 4)
    - Employees (Box 4)
    - Engineering (Box 4)
    - Fire (Box 4)
    - Housing Commission, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Municipal Garage (Box 4)
    - Parks and Recreation (Box 4)
    - Personnel
      - Human rights (Box 4)
      - Policies -- city of Ann Arbor (Box 4)
    - Planning (Box 4)
    - Police, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Purchasing (Box 4)
    - Solid Waste (Box 4)
    - Transportation (Box 4)
    - Treasurer (Box 4)
    - Utilities (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - Letters to University of Michigan athletes (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 5)
    - General correspondence from Mayor's office, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Correspondence May 1985-December 1985, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Proclamations
    - 1983-November 1985, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - January 1986-April 1987, 12 folders (Box 5)
  - Complaint file
    - Papers -- A-W 1986, 13 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Appointment books, 2 volumes (Box 5)
    - Visitors book, 1 volumes (Box 5)
    - Weekly calendar, 1 volumes (Box 5)
    - Clippings (Box 5)
- Post-Mayoral files 1996
  The Post-Mayoral series (0.1 linear ft., 1996) contains a file on Merian's Friends, a physician-aid-in-dying group that Dr. Pierce founded in 1996. The file mainly includes information and newsletters about the group and some photographs.
  - Merian's Friends 1996 (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.1 linear ft.) includes photographs and visual materials covering his mayoral period and photographs of portraits and campaigns.
  - Photographs and visual material (Box 5)
    (Mayoral)
  - Portraits and campaigns (Box 5)
- Sound Recordings: cassette tapes, 1974-1984
  The Sound Recordings series (0.1 linear ft., 1974-1984) contains three audiocassettes of Pierce speaking on issues for various political campaigns.
  - Pierce campaign for Congress ? 1974 (Box 5)
  - Senate race -- issues 1978 (Box 5)
  - "Democratic Warming," 1st AA Church March 3, 1984 (Box 5)
Related material
Researchers interested in Dr. Pierce's medical career may want to consult the Summit Medical Center records at the Bentley Historical Library. More extensive documentation relating to Dr. Pierce's congressional, senatorial, and gubernatorial campaigns can be found in the papers of Robert Alexander, a campaign worker for Edward Pierce.